all right welcome back cohort 6 it's 219
and we're in our first discussion of
chapter 2 so Oli thank you for
facilitating and kick it off and then
let's see what we
go okay thank you uh all right so in
chapter
two uh we delve into I mean uh the main
uh compon one of the main components of
active inference Theory uh namely uh how
to formulate action and perception uh
based on variational approaches so for
perception uh the optimization parameter
that needs to be minimized is the
variational free energy and for the uh
action counterpart the similar parameter
would be uh the expected free energy uh
so basically uh in this chapter we
encounter two of the central equations
of active inference Theory uh which are
equations 2.5 and
2.6 uh one for the variation of free
energy which
formulates how uh the agent or the
cognitive agent
optimizes uh the variation free energy
as its minimization parameter and
similarly in equation uh
2.6 uh we see the same uh same mechanism
as applied to a minimization of the
expected free energy in the case of
action uh but before uh going into the
details of uh what those equations show
and how how they work uh in the context
of active inference it might be helpful
to just uh go through the whole chapter
um I mean
uh in case uh there's
any there's I mean any Gap in the
understanding of what the whole picture
here is so uh
first uh as the title of the section 2.2
suggest perception as inference is one
of the motors of active inference
because uh as we know sometimes uh in
the computational or the traditional
cognitive science uh we treat perception
as uh simple information processing um
mechanism but here in active inference
perception uh is treated as a kind of
inference and not just symbol processing
or information processing approach and
the way to do that is uh to formulate it
in terms of uh basian theor uh base
Theory
so uh in box
2.1 uh there
is this fundamental rule of probability
about I mean sumon product rules which
is which are used uh in base Theory and
then in equation 2 .1 uh The Familiar uh
base theorem
uh uh is introduced and then uh through
an
example in figure
2.1 it shows how exactly priors and
beliefs are formulated and expressed in
base
theorem and later by
using uh by by using those summon
product rules uh we can write the
posteriors uh and specifically the
posteriors in the denominator as a kind
of marginalization over uh over the
probabilities of observations so that's
basically what's been done in equation
2.2 and then uh here on page 20 there's
this a useful distinction between the
notion of surprise as applied in
Psychology or at least folk psychology
and the notion of surprise an active
inference or namely the basian surprise
sometimes it's called surprisal
surprisal function uh so uh basically
the difference between those two
concepts are uh they are obviously
related but they're not actually
identical so when we talk about
psychological surprise it connotes
something about the effective uh notion
of that surprise I mean uh we need to be
uh we need to be affected by uh By An
Unexpected observation in order for us
to be surprised but here when we talk
about basium surprise it's much more
formal and it only
describes uh the degree or the extent of
the unexpected event regardless of how
effectively it influences us as human
observers or cognitive observers so it's
just basically um uh something very
formal and statistical so um one other
key movements of active inference
formulation is the use of callback lier
Divergence uh for the comparison uh uh I
mean uh for the comparison between the
prediction and The observed uh data so
uh the the justification to use callback
lier Divergence comes from uh neon
Pearson Lemma uh which I don't think is
stated explicitly in the text
because uh in uh non Pearson Lema uh it
states that the most efficient statistic
to compare two
distributions is the logarithm of their
likelihood ratios so basically that's
what callback lier Divergence is it's
basically the uh um it's just
um uh the comparison between the
logarithms of the of the likelihood
ratio it's the ratio between two uh
likelihoods so uh here on page 20 we see
the definition of callback lier
Divergence in equation
2.3 and then it's applied to uh the
example from figure
2.1 in order to
calculate uh the difference between uh
the posteriors and the priors uh from
that
example uh and
then okay so here we comes we come to an
interesting discussion about the
difference between biological I mean
about biological inference and
optimality so uh in this case uh
optimality uh can be I mean in active
inference literature optimality is
defined in two distinct way ways so here
in this book optimality is used um as a
as a as a cuss function uh that needs to
be optimized or
minimized so but there's another U
that's basically called basian
optimality but there's another notion of
optimality uh which is called Janes
optimality uh which is used in uh basian
mechanics in order to calculate the dual
aspect of active inference namely cmap
or constraint maximum entropy principle
uh which is the direct mirror uh of or
uh the symmetrical Counterpoint of
fe uh but without going into much
details about how that works and how
that relates to basian inference here
when the word optimality is used in this
book uh it's almost
always uh it almost always means basian
optimality and not Janes
optimality uh okay so uh the view of
active
inference uh
here we treat biological organisms as a
kind of machines uh that do uh that
undertake these um basian optimality in
order to optimize uh the surprisal or
minimize the variation of free energy or
expected free energy and the way they do
that is through a
tripartite um model namely uh the
generative process and generative model
and markup blanket that kind of acts as
an interface between the generative
model and the generative process so very
briefly generative process is what
happens in the environment uh I mean
external to the agent and the generative
model is uh what the
organism
uh
and perceive about the environment or at
least uh anticipate the
environment the data or the latent uh
hidden states of the or latent states of
the environment and uh it constitutes uh
its generative model based on those
processes uh and the way it interacts
with uh the generative process is
through Mark of blanket uh which will
come to uh much more detailed in chapter
3 so here on page 23 we can see this
tripartite um model in figure
2.2 and uh
then as again as the symmetrical
counterpart for perception as action we
can
formulate that mechanism similarly for
the action namely action as inference
and uh the only thing that needs to be
changed in equation
2.5 is the substitution of um is a
substitution of um I mean variation free
energy with the expected free energy so
basically uh those two equations are uh
related to each other and they're
somehow actually the mirror image of
each other or counterparts to each other
so um yeah that's basically uh I mean
the rest of the the rest of the chapters
from 2.5 unto the end of the chapter is
devoted to the derivation of those
Central equations uh which we can talk
about a little bit more detail uh this
week or the next week if you
will thank you Oli awesome
summary does anyone want
to like what's a part that they like to
to or a question or a thought one that
was written in the questions that we can
go to or a new
one I have a question in terms of uh
self assessment so does it in terms of
like creating almost like an atlas in
terms of like say if you utilizing like
a a flow mechanic in terms of active
inference so if you're in a state where
you know you're working on a problem for
example um using a tool and you've
arrived at a certain point how to then
map back without consciously
interrupting um your Flow
State um what's the best way to kind of
map backwards so you can extrapolate any
information forwards so people have
questions you know on how you arrived at
a certain conclusion how you might be
able to uh clarify if that makes
sense there's a lot of that question
like
um know how and know that so is it about
knowing where you've gotten to or
knowing how to navigate forwards or
backwards those might be all the same
answer or it could be all different
answers and going you know swimming up
the river isn't going to help you swim
back down the river or there's a path on
the side of the river um you might be
able to use just passive recording like
recording the screen grab or something
like that so that certain parts could be
checkpointed and and just kind of locked
in I considered like OBX in that sense
um but I was just thinking in terms of
like
storage um you know if there's a way
around that too in terms of like can you
do a direct correlational map kind of
like a neural net to go backwards
through that you could build
out and then apply forwards as
well well on the kind of um incremental
Improvement you could uh use a
time-lapse video in OB yes like you
don't need to take a HD 30 frames per
second you could do like a time lapse
and then to but to kind of bring it to
the generative model side you could come
to develop your own model of perception
and action in the interface with that
tool and then by building out your model
of perception and action with that tool
you might arrive at a very
distilled very reduced parameter
description
yeah I mean that's how I'm kind of
considering it like how can I build
nodes backwards that might give me
inference forwards with you know less
energy input in the future or in the
present like can you build uh naral
nodes that would you know reproduce the
same kind of U predictive
result by examining um you know those
priors and how they changed or branched
from the
origin well I'll try to give one more
active thought on on that like so we're
looking to be building some generative
models something like figure
4.3 so a huge amount of the
actual action selection dependent causal
unfolding of the world is basically all
loaded into B Because D is just a prior
a is just a mapping between observations
and hidden States so basically
everything about like how one's actions
in the world change it going forward is
the expected free energy equation 2.6 B
Matrix here so let's just say that you
were um just doing a a mouse movement
tool um one way to kind of engineer that
would be try to um you know de memorize
or try to reconstruct long sequences of
planned Mouse movements another one
might be just hyper
locally understanding like the gradients
around the mouse location or around the
attention very
locally and then trying to determine
that um attention landscape or that
affordance landscape and then try to um
either find yourself within or create
new can iions of like canalized
attention where to go from point A to
point B it it may be just as simple as
just sliding downhill rather than
needing to like
invoke um symbolic
cues
okay it makes sense I'm just trying to
think I guess it's a little bit more
granular but I was considering more um I
mean depending so personally for myself
I would like to build something I guess
that's more eye tracking because I do
that more I think than Mouse tracking
um but that's a different conversation
for a different day
so I guess it would still be you could
do XY parameterization in that same
sense
but sorry go and if I understood you
correctly uh there is another uh related
uh sub theory of active imprints uh
called branching time active imprint uh
which kind of an attempt to improve the
efficiency of active inference
computation uh by using basian filtering
uh and um so instead of the iteration of
the update equations uh they uh
alternate between integration of the
evidence and the prediction of future
States
so it significantly improves improves
the and U also reduces the complexity
class of the of the algorithms and uh it
improves the benchmarks uh significantly
so uh yeah branching time active
inference is a direct attempt to uh
somehow do those kinds of computations
with much less energy and with much more
efficiency as well okay great thanks
I'll review
that here's kind of a
core image with the two ways that the
discrepancy is addressed or resolved
with like change your mind or change the
world like it's too warm in the room you
know there's a plus it's plus three
degrees too
warm either that can come to be
explained Away by updating belief that
that's the temperature or that can be
changed materially or you know the
tension could be held there but these
are kind of the options when there is a
Divergence and then how agents and the
environment interact um
Thomas oh no I have a question so it's
um oh yeah go for it oh yeah just in
general I didn't want to interrupt I
wasn't meant to inter I'm not reason my
hand to intervene on what's being
proposed talk about right now um just's
a question my question was related to in
the policy section later part of chapter
2 the C parameter related to uh gpie so
the future expect 10 expectation part I
was just curious like because that seems
like a very important that I was curious
I saw there was a that element is there
and it seems like kind a surprising
surprise uh that there's a uh preference
such an important part to play in the I
guess I assume the pragmatic value part
of the equation uh yeah it is it's part
of that section um so I I'd love to hear
I expecting that probably talk more
about in later chapters but that was
just something I caught in my mind just
more about that if there's some just
clarification about where that's coming
from and why that's
there yeah Oli or anyone what is the
preference variable how does it come
into play and how does active ence's
treatment of expect Ed and preferred
observations have similarities and
differences with for example
reinforcement
learning yeah uh so the preference
variable I mean uh it's again one of the
key moves um in active inference to
encode
preferences uh
so uh for expected free
energy I mean if we use the exact
counterpart of equation
2.5 uh then uh I mean we would uh we
wouldn't need uh to incorporate any
other additional parameters uh I mean to
incode preferences or anything like that
but uh one of the uh I mean the
dependence on
policies uh can be dropped from the
pragmatic value term uh that's that's
the idea behind uh the the encoding of
the preferences because um
although in uh some of the earlier
papers of active inference uh it it's
not incorporated into into the
equations uh I mean but uh in recent
papers uh they tend to clearly
distinguish uh this form of the free
energy namely the expected free energy
from the variation free energy by incor
incorporating that pragmatic uh value
explicitly as conditioned on a
preference variable so uh basically uh
the way they do it is to try to again uh
embed the whole
equation um under um or let let me put
it this way uh they U by encoding the
preference the whole equation can be uh
somehow uh uh written down as a kind of
lower bound of uh another optimization
parameter which is which has
incorporated this C parameter or the
preference parameter so uh basically
what it means is that uh by replacing
the true posterior with an approximate
posterior uh this uh pragmatic value can
be explicitly conditioned
uh pragmatic value can be explicitly
conditioned on um the the preference
variable C so
uh by flipping the the terms inside that
expectation value uh it can be uh it can
be treated as the exact opposite of uh
the variational free energy without
compromising uh I mean the symmetrical
relationship between those two uh so but
why the epistemic value term here is
important well because obviously
uh so take for instance if we're in a
dark room
uh there's this pous problem dark room
problem the mapping between the hidden
States and the and the observations
would be entirely ambiguous so uh the
best way to reduce this ambiguity is to
uh uh somehow uh seek out the
observations that uh reduce this
uncertainty by U maximizing the change
from prior to posterior belief after a
new observation or uh similarly uh by um
uh I mean reducing the uncertainty about
those hidden states by reducing the the
variation of free energy so uh by
applying the epistemic value here it uh
provid Ides a way to navigate that space
of possibilities when the agent tries to
uh maximize its certainty about the
posterior belief uh so yeah that's one
of the key differences between the
earlier active inference literature from
about up until uh
2021 and the later ones from 20 uh
21 uh up to recent
papers thanks a little more on C so this
is the PDP partially observable Markov
decision process and every letter here
is like a statistical
distribution or a variable in the
program so defining the active inference
agent is defining the a b c and and d
and so on so this is like defining the
whole agent in its unfolding and so we
can look at each of the nodes as
statistical distributions or
parameterized and then also when there's
an edge which is like a causal
relationship it's an influence so we can
talk about that as a conditional value
like conditioned upon this being the
case what does this and so that's the
vertical line here so how does active
inference deal with goal oriented
behavior so it's a big question but at
this kind of minimal essential level the
key move is to define a preference
distribution explicitly over
observations so in reward or
reinforcement learning you'd have
observations coming in like let's just
say we're talking about body temperature
and different body temperatures would be
associated with how rewarding they are
and then movement would be performed to
move to more rewarding States and
utility discounting and all these other
kind of ad hoc um issues arising in
contrast what happens in the kind of a
preference orientation in active
inference which doesn't need to exist at
all you could remove have a flat
preference distribution and just have
purely epistemic Behavior or or you
could have purely preference driven
Behavior but what happens here is that
the preferences which is hence the the
origin of the joke preference slash
expectation like what do you expect and
prefer is going to happen how does it
become a self-fulfilling prophecy
because there's a coincidence of the
preferred and the expected in
self-fulfilling agent so then the
preference is explicitly the
distribution of body temperatures so
when I'm at 37 degrees it's not like I'm
in the most rewarding State and then if
I drop down to 36 I need to increase my
reward back by going to 37 it's actually
I'm more surprised by being at 36 than
37 and the ball rolls back downhill to
the bottom of the bowl resting in the
low surprise State the most preferred
the most expected the bottom of the bowl
rather than trying to Hill Climb a
secondarily proposed reward function or
utility function that's scaffolded on an
observation
distribution so observations are not
secondarily
evaluated there's just the definition of
a preference over
observations and that kind of grounds
the model it's kind of like having it
touch grass because otherwise how would
the actions
come to um influence in this way that is
control like um the the fundamental
piece of the model and then just last
piece here um here's the G equation 2.6
expected free energy and then this is
just showing how when you remove or zero
out certain components of this equation
how you get other well-known forms like
if you remove epistemic value all of 2
three four five so all you retain is
this pragmatic value of future
observations conditioned upon
preferences you get expected utility
Theory whereas if you drop pragmatic
value and only have epistemic value you
have novelty maximization Infomax Etc so
this is kind of like a
generalization on a bigger space of
decision-making possibilities that run
the gamut from arbitrarily pragmatic to
arbitrarily epistemic and all of their
mixtures
David yeah so I just had a question
related to um you said rolling back down
um the bow so in terms of I'm just
trying to think of it analogously um
wouldn't that be kind of return to
priors but that in that sense would you
bring your new experience back down into
the bowl therefore expanding the priors
as well or would it be combinational in
a certain
way or bringing that back out of that
lower state to that reward State and
then back down would that
transfer any difference between the two
states it's a great question there's
been some work on C learning preference
learning so the easy setting is if
preferences are a priori fixed then um
yes the pragmatic component of the agent
will just just like a moth for a flame
just like it will just keep trying to
get to see and so maybe for like
thermostat or something like a fixed C
makes sense um then you could have a
higher order control policy on C that's
one option or Andor you could have C
learning now C learning is a bit of a
challenge because if you just updated
your preferences to whatever was
happening you might as well not have
preferences like if you just kept on
reup dating what temperature you
preferred to just whatever temperature
was in the room you might as well just
be going with whatever is happening in
the room okay so it's more more of a
recomposition in that
sense or
Reformation um can I add something uh in
in answer to your question sorry uh so
okay uh if I mean uh the
uh probability of observation
conditioned on C uh is totally different
from the prior over stat because um
prior Over States only uh encode beliefs
about the true states of the word uh
irrespective of the preference or what
is preferred but uh in this formulation
uh we uh by using uh the condition I
mean by using uh the preference value
see the observations with higher
probabilities are treated as more
rewarding so it's a kind of reward
function uh if you will right but uh
again it's totally different from the
prior Over States uh and um also another
Point uh this kind of formulation
enables u a kind
of planning as inference which is
distinct from both perception as
inference and action as inference right
because here uh the use of these
probability distributions to incode
preferences and policy values uh is a
kind of um it brings the elements of
action selection uh within the domain of
basian belief updating uh and the key
paper uh on that is uh Kaplan and
friston's 2018 paper namely um let me
yeah find the name of the paper it's
something about yeah it's planning and
navigation as active inference
so this seemingly simple trick of using
uh the preference value here uh again
enables another form of inference which
is completely different from the
previous ones as
well okay great thank
you
does anyone want to um ask a question or
we can look at upvoted questions or we
can look at any
other
question
a lot happens in two this is kind of the
first technical
chapter and it's the low road with the
how
Peter hi there um so I did have one
question about
the um the kind of like triart type
model that's shown on page
23 um so I understand the idea that
um I'm trying to sorry just use the the
correct terms here
um so so there's there's two hidden
states that are listed one that
corresponds to the world and one that
corresponds to uh like the agent's model
I understand the the concept of why the
hidden State associated with the process
would be hidden because it's on the
other side of like a marov blanket why
would the hidden State associated with
the model be hidden like what is that
what's the sort of implication
there go for it Ellie
uh okay so the uh the implication of uh
using the hidden state in the model um I
mean by by using u
x
wait I sto hearing
only uh okay can you hear me yeah yeah
go ahead
okay uh so by including X in the
generative model uh it so the X asterisk
is the true value of hidden State uh
which is in the generative process right
and in generative model the agent tries
to model to or tries to perceive as
accurately as possible the true value of
hidden state in the generative process
say but uh obviously it can't be done uh
through direct perception or any kind of
uh with any level of U complete
certainty uh and it can only be done uh
probabilistically so uh the reason on
one side it's only X and on the other
side it's X ASX is to uh distinguish
between those two values of x one being
the true one the other
being the inferred one right uh so here
the X as hidden state in the generator
model is actually the inferred hidden
state of the true value of hidden state
in the generative process so I'm not
sure if it's helpful or not but yeah
I'll add a few more pieces um close
synonyms first off there's many um kind
of natural language assertions and
descriptions that don't interfere with
this essential particular
partition um which one of which I'll
explain but the hidden State also
sometimes called an external state or a
latent State um but it its external is
hidden from the internal via the blanket
and also there's a sense in which this
is hidden from the point of view of the
environment and that symmetry um here is
a kind of very fun um kind of Light
breaking post textbook Group which is
here's what we were just looking
at generative model generative process
but then
later we see um ramstead and others
using generative model as system level
description and then in this video and
transcript um Ali
basically asks that
specifically so suffice to say that when
you're working with
multi-agent simulations or where there's
agents communicating across an interface
it isn't always the most useful to be
talking about internal and external
because internal is always just
specifically from one reference point so
if you're talking about ecosystems of
shared intelligence
then the way that they're addressing
that with with no fundamental change in
the actual topology of the model which
is really what defines the variables
um at least they are using more
generative model to describe the
total
constructed model representation so not
just not focusing on partitioning
generative model from process but again
these are different natural language
assertions on top of the same exact
formalities but it just can be a little
bit unclear because sometimes people are
talking about the environment as
generative process but then it's like
but if the environment is another agent
then doesn't it have a generative model
and what are we really talking about
well again the variables in the math or
the variables in the computer program
when you build it it wouldn't matter if
you described it one way or the other
per se but this more recent is just a
simpler more
inclusive um way to describe it however
it's also not the distinction between
generative model and process that the
textbook in insists on which is it's
accurate it's not like it's going to
mislead it's just that you'll also see
people talking about generative model in
a little bit of a broader
way David then
Thomas yeah so uh just in terms of
concept so I'm a little behind on some
of the uh terminology so I'm just trying
to grasp it a little bit more so I was
just thinking in terms of the Markoff
blanket
um as an opaque State versus a
transparent St so we updating are we
able to is it kind of like a
transference through that field state to
another higher state or is it you know
more of a transparency of the field
being able to glean context from you
know what is behind that and in that
sense you know going back to the model
that you were just showing if we are
let's say capable of generating
something that includes the model the
inferred State and the process wouldn't
we then create another blanket
encompassing the
whole and then how would you approach
that in terms of you know are you not
reproducing at the same time a new
state these are great questions yeah go
ahead Ellie okay sorry okay so the whole
idea behind markup blanket and the
justification for its use uh lies behind
the concept of sparse coupling so in a
complex multi-dimensional a agents or
systems uh there's a kind of sparse
coupling between the agent and the
environment in the sense that uh the
agent doesn't have any direct access to
the environment and uh the causal
relationship between uh the disturbances
of the environment or any kind of data
of the environment and uh its causal
effect uh on the internal state of of
the agent is uh completely nonlinear or
as friston himself would like to call
it's caused vicariously it's not direct
but uh it's kind of indirect in causal
INF influence on the internal states of
the agent so in that sense yes we can
say the markup blanket is kind of opaque
it's not transparent in the sense that
there is a
direct uh I mean transparent lens or
direct access to um environment to
external uh States and data but on the
other hand uh there's this notion of
basing lens which has developed uh
recently uh through category
the L yeah it is opaque they've explored
that in the phenomenology setting like
metser opaque states of mind and they've
really mapped that closely to the
blankie concept it's also opaque but but
shines through that's why it's the
holographic blanket and then you're
totally right you can design or imagine
special
situations like where you know once
you're dealing with metacognitive agents
or counteract like you can end up with
some
very creative and and twisted
settings and then it just like well you
can make a map where San Francisco has
you know an underground railroad and all
these other things it's like okay and
then
those the map the map play can be
infinite
okay it's interesting thank you thank
you
Thomas yeah the build on what Peter was
asking originally with the hidden States
um yeah we give it more is this a Kind
part of the distinction of AC and policy
discussed in this chapter in that sense
of what we just what you just said where
the hypothetical
counterfactual operations uh they seem
to operate in in likelihoods as opposed
to kind conf your probabilities uh so it
seems like at least in my notes I had
about that that the hidden States like
basically the I guess expected X in the
formulation is a segment or a trajectory
of a hidden State over time and that's
against or I guess uh conditionalized to
Pi the condition the conditional
trajectories on the policies so just
like there's some clarification about
that yes okay so let's think about Tilda
is the real temperature in the room
Through Time Tilda is just sequence
through time we're prospectively talking
about action now not all things
prospectively plan action so vfe 2.5
might be sufficient if we were talking
about like a rock but we're talking
about something that's actually engaging
in that counterfactual so the real
temperature in the room X Tilda through
time and then the observations Through
Time on the thermometer um so one of the
decompositions that we talk about the
most with expected free energy and the
one that aligns it the most with those
other models shown earlier of like
decision-making is this epistemic and
pragmatic value um distinction but that
decomposition is exactly equivalent to
first off the physics based energy minus
entropy form that's what makes it a free
energy but then these middle two forms
and these are linked um here is um how
ambiguous both have the same first term
which is how ambiguous what's the
entropy the policy dependent entropy of
the mapping between thermometer readings
and the temperature in the room so both
first terms are basically saying like um
policies are better when they're less
ambiguous in their sensory mapping and
then this second term is basically um
very similar looking the only difference
is here there's a y Tilda versus an X
Tilda
um because whatever our our action
selection dependence uncertainty about
thermometer readings is if we had a
perfectly accurate
thermometer our risk over thermometer
readings would be the same as the risk
over temperature in the room and then to
the extent that we have even a tiny tiny
bit of noise in the thermometer we're
always more unsure about the temperature
in the room than we are about the
thermometer readings because these are
the the approximate Target of estimation
of like preferences and then there's
always further uncertainty Beyond
observables so H how exactly complex
like
World unfoldings get wrapped into this
that is the the challenge of making the
relevant
model and what's interesting is that
even if you write the equation and you u
in your program and it calculates it
this way
you're also Computing a quantity or
scoring measure that has these
equivalent
interpretations but this is usually how
it's
written but then that's equivalent to
this physics based one this is the
control theory based one and then here's
kind of like a Investment Portfolio type
one
just wanted to say uh thanks for that
explanation I think my misunderstanding
uh with regards to X was thinking that
hidden there meant something like hidden
from the agent's perspective or like
metacognitively inaccessible um so this
is very clarifying thank
you yeah like which es especially when
dealing with a complex cognitive entity
that like could have access or not to
its own State it's kind of like this
simple case is just we're writing the
software for a thermometer and air
conditioner and it just has Total Access
to the variables we're not going to
worry about the phenomenology or like
whether they something that's shielded
from itself or not um and and then again
in this minimal case like the aboutness
of X is exactly the the this x star the
real temperature in the room but you
could have a situation where the
temperature in the room causes the
lights to change
and then the agent has a has a model
where the Laten State it's inferring is
bitcoin price and it thinks that that's
a causal relationship with the lights
changing in the
room and like it will do its best with
the knobs that it has access to this is
kind of what variational methods are
given the the suite or the scope of the
knobs that it can change it will do its
best with a KL Divergence minimization
to to make the best
approximation but that doesn't even mean
that the aboutness of its model is like
remotely the
same like one case that's often talked
about well this could be a continuous
variable outside and then the agent
could just be saying too hot just right
or too cold so like the type of variable
and the aboutness of the variable can be
very
different
David yeah so I'm still trying to grasp
this and think I'm close but I'm not
sure so I'm kind of looking at this in
terms of analogously like unknown
unknowns and how that would update our
own priors um where you know we may not
be conscious I don't want to use the
word consciously but aware um that our
priors are being updated and then we do
externalize them
later I guess at what point do we then
re internalize them as
active good good question so let's just
say that we had a kind of a cognitively
like structurally cognitively fixed
robot um and uh then it doesn't even
have the
possibility to like uh like let's just
say it's inferring the the location of
one you know it's hunting one prey but
actually there's two out there or
there's none or something it's like it
will keep on doing what it can without
one with trying trying to find the
position of one um prey item and then um
higher and higher levels of
flexibility could could start to address
a greater diversity of real settings
externally but then that unknown unknown
is a really interesting question because
surprise is kind of like a um an
agnostic or or pronostic even um alarm
signal
because the an increase in Surprise due
to the the
temperature um reading that might be
like kind of a a Known Unknown like I
can deal with this kind of temperature
increase we've done it before or it
could be something structurally
different happening in the world that
basically no action is going to be able
to address right and then that's where
like the structure learning comes into
play and it's like okay well now let's
propose new latent causes
like wow the one cause model of
temperature in the room is is is
surprising I'm going to propose a two
cause model of
temperature and then like that the
abductive process of proposing new
accounts but but even that can can still
be beset with unknown
unknowns right I guess I was approaching
it in terms of and this I might go
beyond the scope a little bit but in
terms of sensory perception so like you
know we have our five main senses but
that's what's known to us right in terms
of conceptualizing it there might be you
know trending towards an infinite number
of sensory inputs that you know the
brain might process differently which we
might find as you know our modeling gets
better and we deal more with cybernetics
and you know evolution in that sense
aren't we kind of fixing the model in
that
sense and not accounting for those extra
sensory unknowns that might be
incorporated later and would it require
then a complete reconstruction of the
model as we are conceptualizing
it
um with the metaphor of
LEGOs this is like the minimal Lego
tetrahedra four pieces this is the
minimal um you know pick it up and and
juggle with it Four Legos that are put
together that makes a total cognitive
simulation now if you want to deal with
where there's like higher order like
volitional or
adaptive structural changes to the
model just by sketching it out you can
see that the state space is going to
expand like Mega exponentially very
fast um so to do adaptive search or even
persistence in like structurally
volatile spaces is a very large question
so it w it wouldn't um unseat the basian
mechanics or make something simpler than
this but certainly you could make things
way larger than this graph that have a
lot of those kinds of like reflexive
structural modification and structure
learning it's just that in practice
first off not all of those um capacities
have been brought from the code and the
research or sorry from the research and
the math into the code so sometimes that
would need to be like implemented um ad
hoc in in a software package but we hope
to build that into the open source
packages and so on and then even if the
capacity has been translated from the
math into the code like structure
learning has been then there's often a
really really large optimization or
parameter sweep step because you're just
increasing the the state space of the
model so vastly okay so this is kind of
your gen state right for your your seed
growth basically so everything's going
to grow out of this despite you know
where it may grow too in that
sense like through the expansion we can
still go back to that base
model yeah like the the this uh
structure learning is like proposing
another latent cause and then asking
whether the the more um the higher model
complexity has sufficiently improved
accuracy and then there's basian model
reduction which is you take your model
and you ask like which of these
parameters is like the worst and which
one can I reduce out and so with this
kind of like plus one and minus one
parameter moves structure learning and
basing model reduction that's kind of
like that's like the AGI ACM kind of
dream SL meme would be you'd start with
a single state space and then there
would be a process that autonomously or
or in a scaffolded way that the agent
would basically propose alternatives to
its own model including like arbitrary
or higher order levels of whatever
cognitive State and then guiding that
kind of neuromorphic evolution again
it's an even larger State space yet it
would have like perhaps some of these um
qualities like parsimony or um like
ability to reproducibly develop
appropriately and so
on okay great thank
you well we'll
return next time for more low
road um up Vote or add more questions
and then if like you want to make sure
that it gets addressed because we didn't
look at too many of these just tag or
something and then at this time next
week that will be discreet Time chapter
7 in the cohort 5 which is kind of like
the models we were discussing today with
the
pdps hence why bouncing back and forth
and everything with the chapters is all
good so thank you all till next time
bye thanks guys have a good one